{"tossups": [{"question": "This man\u2019s willingness to testify as a character witness convinced a judge to drop an anti-Communist trial against W.E.B. Du Bois. This scientist\u2019s namesake field equations can be used to calculate spacetime geometry and includes the cosmological constant, which is referred to as this scientist\u2019s \u201cbiggest blunder.\u201dIn 1952, this scientist was offered the presidency of Israel. For ten points, name this scientist who developed the theory of relativity and the equation E equals m c squared.", "answer": "Albert<b> Einstein</b>", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {"question": "In the build-up to this case, Shirley Wheeler was arrested and charged with manslaughter. This case, decided at the same time as<em> Doe v. Bolton</em>, was eventually opposed by its own plaintiff who had converted to Catholicism. Norma McCorvey brought forth this case whose aspect of fetal viability was reaffirmed in <em>Casey v. Planned Parenthood</em>. For ten points, name this 1973 court case that legalized abortions.", "answer": "<b> Roe</b> v. Wade", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This political party\u2019s principles were outlined in the Tamworth Manifesto, written by Robert Peel as a way to separate his policies from those of his ally, the Duke of Wellington. A modern leader of this party took power after the \u201cWinter of Discontent,\u201d replacing James Callaghan in 1979. For ten points, name this British political party whose members, like Margaret Thatcher, are commonly known as \u201cTories.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Conservative</b> (and Unionist) Party (prompt on \u201cTories\u201d before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "If not soaked in alkali water, depending on this staple crop can cause pellagra through Vitamin B3 deficiency. In Mesoamerica, archaeologists can tell which people were city-dwelling versus rural-dwelling by whether their teeth show cavities from eating this crop. With squash and climbing beans, this crop is part of the \u201cThree Sisters\u201d of agriculture in North America. For ten points, name this cereal grain that is also known as maize.", "answer": "<b> corn</b> (accept<b> maize</b> before mentioned) Page 1", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "In the ground portion of this campaign, the London Irish Rifles captured four soldiers in the Battle of the Graveney Marsh. The failure of this campaign led one side to cancel Operation Sea Lion, a planned amphibious invasion. In response to this campaign, Winston Churchill praised the pilots of the Royal Air Force. The Blitz attacks on London followed, for ten points, what air campaign against Great Britain carried out by Nazi Germany?", "answer": "<b> Battle of Britain</b> (accept The<b> Air Battle for England</b>; accept<b> Luftschlacht um England</b>; do not accept or prompt on \u201cThe Blitz\u201d) (8) A 2016 mass shooting of police in this city ended when a robot delivered a bomb to this city\u2019s El Centro College. Officer JD Tippit was shot and killed in this city shortly after another shooting that took place in this city\u2019s Dealey Plaza. For ten points, name this city where a Texas School Book Depository was the staging point for Lee Harvey Oswald\u2019s assassination of John F. Kennedy. ANSWER:<b> Dallas</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "While contesting power over Silk Road cities in the Fergana Valley, this empire defeated the Tang Dynasty at the River Talas. A ruler of this empire gifted Charlemagne both an elephant and a water clock that perplexed his court. This empire, which was later centered in Mamluk Egypt, had its capital sacked in the 13th century by Hulagu Khan. For ten points, name this empire that built Baghdad and succeeded the Umayyads.", "answer": "<b> Abbasid</b> Caliphate <b>Second Quarter</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man was mocked by the press for being attacked by a \u201ckiller rabbit\u201d while fishing in a swamp. In an interview for<em> Playboy</em>, this man admitted that he had \u201ccommitted adultery\u201d in his heart \u201cmany times.\u201d This man stated that America was facing a \u201ccrisis of confidence\u201d in his Malaise speech, which focused on the on-going energy crisis. The Iran Hostage Crisis hurt the approval rating of, for ten points, what President who lost the Election of 1980 to Ronald Reagan?", "answer": "James \u201cJimmy\u201d<b> Carter</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The losers of this battle suffered from Quintus Dellius defecting and giving their battle plans to the enemy. The smaller and quicker Liburnian ships fought against a smaller force of quinqueremes near the Ambracian Gulf in this battle. The victory of Marcus Agrippa at this battle allowed a leader to take the title \u201cPrinceps\u201d and usher in the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this 31 BC naval battle in which Augustus defeated Marc Antony and his Egyptian allies.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Actium</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In this election year, Shepard Fairey made a poster of the winning candidate in solid red, beige, and blue. One candidate in this election year called his opponent \u201ca decent family man\u201d after an audience member labeled that opponent \u201can Arab.\u201d The winning candidate in this year used the slogan \u201cYes We Can,\u201d and ran with Delaware senator Joe Biden. For ten points, name this election year in which John McCain lost to Barack Obama.", "answer": "US presidential election of<b> 2008</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "He later became the Republican presidential candidate in 2012.", "answer": "Willard \u201cMitt\u201d<b> Romney</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In the aftermath of this battle, the body of the winning commander was stored in a barrel of brandy for transport. The flagship of Admiral Collingwood, the<em> Royal Sovereign</em> took heavy damage in this battle. A commander in this battle signaled \u201cEngland expects every man to do his duty\u201d after he drove his ships towards a French fleet. Horatio Nelson was killed in, for ten points, what 1805 battle off the coast of Spain that Britain won?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Trafalgar</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This thinker developed a phonetic alphabet that abandoned so-called \u201credundant letters\u201d such as \u201cc, j, q, w, x, and y.\u201d Letters from Thomas Hutchinson about cracking down on Bostonians were deliberately leaked by this man. This politician was appointed the first United States Postmaster General by the Continental Congress. For ten points, name this Pennsylvanian founding father who flew a kite during a lightning storm.", "answer": "Benjamin<b> Franklin</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Ice nearly prevented Henry Knox from completing this action with 18 artillery pieces. Shortly before this action took place, Thomas Paine\u2019s</b><em><b> The American Crisis</b></em><b> was read to</b> <b>a group of men whose enlistment ended on (+)</b> <b>Christmas. An 1851 Emanuel Leutze</b> <b>[LOYT-zuh] painting shows James Monroe standing and Nathaniel Greene leaning over the edge of a (*) </b> boat while performing this action. The Battle of Trenton followed, for ten points, what military movement undertaken at night by Washington\u2019s Revolutionary Army in December 1776?", "answer": "(George Washington and/or the Continental Army)<b> crossing the Delaware</b> River", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>During this event, John Richards warned his congregation against a reliance on spectral</b> <b>evidence. A man executed by pressing during this event demanded (+)</b> <b>\u201cmore weight\u201d</b> <b>rather than plead guilty. Giles Corey was killed during this event, which started when (*) </b>Sarah Good, Sarah Osborne, and Tituba were arrested for causing two girls to go into epileptic fits. For ten points, name this 1692 event in which over a dozen women were executed for allegedly practicing magic in a Massachusetts town.", "answer": "<b> Salem Witch Trials</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>According to William Julius Wilson, this concept\u2019s importance is declining due to the complex nature of job markets. In</b><em><b> The Bell Curve</b></em><b>, Charles Murray linked differences in</b> <b>intelligence to this concept. \u201cOne (+)</b> <b>intelligence to this concept. \u201cOne (+)</b> <b>drop\u201d rules have been used to classify this concept,</b> <b>and (*)</b> poll taxes and literacy tests were used in the Jim Crow South to discriminate based on this poll taxes and literacy tests were used in the Jim Crow South to discriminate based on this concept. For ten points, name this sociological concept that may be divided on census forms into types like black, white, and Asian.", "answer": "<b> race</b> (accept<b> ethnicity</b>) Page 8", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Sociology"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A war in this country centered around Villmergen led to the annihilation of a religious community in Schwyz [SHVOOTZ]. Catholics and Protestants in this country clashed in the</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Kappel Wars. Ulrich Zwingli brought Anabaptism to this country. This country was</b> <b>Kappel Wars. Ulrich Zwingli brought Anabaptism to this country. This country was</b> <b>the site of the (*)</b> <b>the site of the (*)</b> Sonderbund War, in which regions like Valais and Lucerne allied to fight against centralized authority. For ten points, name this country where John Calvin spread his teachings while living in Geneva.", "answer": "<b> Switzerland</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s wife, Betty Shabazz, was killed in 1997 after her ten year old grandson</b> <b>set her apartment on fire. In the aftermath of the assassination of (+)</b> <b>John F.</b> <b>Kennedy, this man was censured for calling it \u201cchickens coming home to roost.\u201d This man was assassinated at the (*)</b> Audubon Ballroom for publicly criticizing Elijah Muhammad. For ten points, name this former Nation of Islam activist who changed his last name to reflect his stolen African heritage.", "answer": "<b> Malcolm X</b> (accept Malcolm<b> Little</b>; accept El-Hajj Malik El-<b>Shabazz</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}